# João Pedro Dias

Department of Informatics Enginnering Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto INESC TEC Porto, Portugal Last updated: May, 2019 ORCID: 0000-0001-9066-6436 email: jpmdias@fe.up.pt website: jpdias.me

**Summary** João Pedro Dias has an MSc in Informatics and Computing Engineering by the Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto. He is a Ph.D. student of the Doctoral Program in Informatics Engineering by the same university since 2017. He is an Invited Assistant Lecturer at FEUP since 2017 and has co-supervised 4 MSc dissertations. Has participated as Researcher in 2 projects at LIACC and INESC TEC (Porto, Portugal). Works in the area of Software Engineering, with a special interest in Design Patterns, Internet-of-Things, and Security.

#### PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

# 2017- Invited Assistant Lecturer

Department of Informatics Engineering (DEI), Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

#### 2017– Researcher

Centre for Information Systems and Computer Graphics (CSIG) Institute for Systems and Computer Engineering (INESC TEC), Technology and Science, Porto, Portugal

# 2016–2017 Researcher

LIACC – Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science Laboratory University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

# 2015–2015 Summer Engineering Intern

ShiftForward, S.A. (now Velocidi) Porto, Portugal

# 2014–2014 IT Department Internship

Centro Hospitalar do Tâmega e Sousa, E.P.E. Penafiel, Porto, Portugal

#### **EDUCATION**

2016– **Ph.D. in Informatics Engineering** – **ProDEI (PhD)**, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Porto, Portugal
Work under Supervision of Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD and Co-Supervision of João Pascoal Faria, PhD

2011–2016 M.Sc. Informatics and Computing Engineering – MIEIC (MSc), Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Porto, Portugal GPA: 15 out of 20

2008–2011 **Elementary School – Sciences and Technologies**, Externato de Vila Meã,

Porto, Portugal GPA: 17 out of 20

# **TEACHING**

#### Invited Assistant Lecturer

Integrated Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering  $\cdot$  FEUP  $\cdot$  5 years

2017-2018 2018-2019

		Year	ECTS	Class	ses
Object Oriented Programming Laborator	y LPOO	2	6	-	1
Operating Systems	SOPE	2	6	2	1
Software Development Laboratory	LDSO	4	7,5	-	1
Software Systems Architecture	ASSO	4	6	-	1

# **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **PREPRINTS**

João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "State of the Software Development Life-Cycle for the Internet-of-Things". In: *CoRR* abs/1811.04159 (2018). arXiv: 1811.04159. URL: http://arxiv.org/abs/1811.04159

# PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

D. Pinto, João Pedro Dias, and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "Dynamic Allocation of Serverless Functions in IoT Environments". In: 2018 IEEE 16th International Conference on Embedded and Ubiquitous Computing (EUC). Oct. 2018, pp. 1–8. DOI: 10.1109/EUC.2018.00008

João Pedro Dias, F. Couto, A. C. R. Paiva, and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "A Brief Overview of Existing Tools for Testing the Internet-of-Things". In: 2018 IEEE International Conference on Software Testing, Verification and Validation Workshops (ICSTW). Apr. 2018, pp. 104–109. DOI: 10.1109/ICSTW.2018.00035

João Pedro Dias, João Pascoal Faria, and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "A Reactive and Model-Based Approach for Developing Internet-of-Things Systems". In: 2018 11th International Conference on the Quality of Information and Communications Technology (QUATIC). Sept. 2018, pp. 276–281. DOI: 10.1109/QUATIC.2018.00049

João Pedro Pinto, João Pedro Dias, and R. J. F. Rossetti. "Growing Smart Cities on an Open-Data-Centric Cyber-Physical Platform". In: 2018 IEEE International Smart Cities Conference (ISC2). Sept. 2018, pp. 1–6. DOI: 10.1109/ISC2.2018.8656989

João Pedro Dias, Hugo Sereno Ferreira, and Ângelo Martins. "A Blockchain-Based Scheme for Access Control in e-Health Scenarios". In: *Proceedings of the Tenth International Conference on Soft Computing and Pattern Recognition (SoCPaR 2018)*. Ed. by Ana Maria Madureira, Ajith Abraham, Niketa Gandhi, Catarina Silva, and Mário Antunes. Cham: Springer International Publishing, 2020, pp. 238–247. ISBN: 978-3-030-17065-3. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-030-17065-3\_24

Guilherme Vieira Pinto, João Pedro Dias, and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "Blockchain-Based PKI for Crowdsourced IoT Sensor Information". In: *Proceedings of the Tenth International Conference on Soft Computing and Pattern Recognition (SoCPaR 2018)*. Ed. by Ana Maria Madureira, Ajith Abraham, Niketa Gandhi, Catarina Silva, and Mário Antunes. Cham: Springer International Publishing, 2020, pp. 248–257. ISBN: 978-3-030-17065-3. DOI: 10.1007/978-3-030-17065-3\_25

Antonio Ramadas, Gil Domingues, Joao Pedro Dias, Ademar Aguiar, and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "Patterns for Things that Fail". In: *Proceedings of the 24th Conference on Pattern Languages of Programs*. PLoP '17. ACM - Association for Computing Machinery, 2017

João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto, and José Magalhães Cruz. "A Hands-on Approach on Botnets for Behavior Exploration". In: *Proceedings of the 2nd International Conference on Internet of Things, Big Data and Security.* SCITEPRESS - Science and Technology Publications, 2017, pp. 463–469. ISBN: 978-989-758-245-5. DOI: 10.5220/0006392404630469

#### PEER-REVIEWED JOURNALS

João Pedro Dias, Ângelo Martins, and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "A Blockchain-based Approach for Access Control in eHealth Scenarios". In: *Journal of Information Assurance and Security* 13 (4 2018), pp. 125–136

# Informal Publications & Others

Filipa Barros, Luis Sousa, João Pedro Dias, and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "A Preliminary Study on Mesh Networks and IoT". in: Book of Abstracts of the 11th Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2018) (2018)

João Pedro Dias and Hugo Sereno Ferreira. "Automating the Extraction of Static Content and Dynamic Behaviour from e-Commerce Websites". In: Book of Abstracts of the 10th Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2017) (2017)

João Pedro Dias, José Pedro Pinto, and José Magalhães Cruz. "A hands-on approach on botnets for a learning purpose". In: Book of Abstracts of the 9th Meeting of Young Researchers of University of Porto (IJUP 2016) (2016)

#### DISSERTATIONS

João Pedro Dias. "Reverse Engineering Static Content and Dynamic Behaviour of E-Commerce Sites for Fun and Profit". Master's Dissertation, Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Supervised by Hugo Sereno Ferreira. 2016. URL: http://hdl.handle.net/10216/85374

#### EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES

## MASTER'S DISSERTATION CO-SUPERVISION

2018– Industrial IoT Remote Debugger by Andreia Rodrigues

Advisor: Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD

Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

2017–2018 Dynamic Allocation of Serverless Functions in IoT Environments by Duarte Pinto, 10216/114149

Advisor: Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD

Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

Blockchain as a PKI for Ownership Control of IoT Devices by Guilherme Pinto,  $\frac{10216}{114144}$ 

Advisor: Hugo Sereno Ferreira, PhD

Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

2016–2017 Interoperability In Software Applications For Smart Cities: Towards A Reference Architecture by José Pedro Pinto, 10216/107529

Advisor: Rosaldo Rossetti, PhD

Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, Porto, Portugal

# **PROJECTS**

- 2017–2018 NanoSTIMA: Macro-to-Nano Human Sensing: Towards Integrated Multimodal Health Monitoring and Analytics, Researcher at INESC TEC Reference NORTE-01-0145-FEDER-000016, nanostima.inesctec.pt
- 2016–2017 PEDDIR DEMO: Weigth in motion and wheels defect detection (Sistema de Pesagem Dinâmica e Deteção de Irregularidades dos Rodados), Researcher at LIACC

Reference NORTE-01-0247-FEDER-006397, peddir.eu

#### PRESENTATIONS & WORKSHOPS

Slides and abstracts for all presentations are available at speakerdeck.com/jpdias

- João Pedro Dias. "Internet-of-broken-Things: A highly-opinionated overview".

  0xOPOSEC Meetup. 2019. URL: https://www.meetup.com/0xOPOSEC/

  João Pedro Dias. "Unravelling the Web of Things: Exploring Mozilla Things

  Framework (Workshop)". Pivels Camp v3.0 by Bright Pivel. 2017. URL: https://www.meetup.com/0xOPOSEC/
  - Framework (Workshop)". Pixels Camp v3.0 by Bright Pixel. 2017. URL: https://pixels.camp
- João Pedro Dias. "PiHeadquarters or How to Take Control of your House with Raspberry Pi and Docker (Workshop)". Pixels Camp v2.0 by Bright Pixel. 2017. URL: https://pixels.camp
- João Pedro Dias and José Pedro Pinto. "A hands-on approach on botnets for a learning purpose". 0xOPOSEC Meetup. 2016. URL: https://www.meetup.com/0x0POSEC/
- João Pedro Dias and José Pedro Pinto. "How To Create Your First Personal Webpage". ShARE World Seminar 2015 "Europe vs. Asia: Grass Is Always Greener On The Other Side". 2015. URL: http://www.share-share.org/world-seminar/

# **ACADEMIC SERVICE & AFFILIATIONS**

### REVIEWER

IEEE Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IEEE IV 2017) – IEEE 20<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (IEEE ITSC 2017) – IEEE International Symposium on Personal, Indoor and Mobile Radio Communications (IEEE PIMRC 2019)

# COMMITTEES

- 2019 **Track Chair**, Symposium on Informatics Engineering, part of the 3<sup>rd</sup> Doctoral Congress Engineering (DCE19)
  - **Program Committee Member**, Talk a Bit Student Organized Tech Conference, 7<sup>th</sup> Edition (2019)
- 2018 **Makerspace Chair**, 19<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Agile Software Development (XP 2018)
  - Conference Organization Chair, 13<sup>th</sup> Doctoral Symposium in Informatics Engineering (DSIE'18)
  - **Advisor Board Member**, Talk a Bit Student Organized Tech Conference,  $6^{\rm th}$  Edition (2018)
- 2017 **Program Committee Member**, 2017 IEEE 1<sup>st</sup> Summer School on Smart Cities (IEEE S3C 2017)

**Web Communication Co-chai**r, The Second ACM International Workshop on Smart, Autonomous, and Connected Vehicular Systems and Services (ACM CarSys 2017), part of the The 23<sup>rd</sup> Annual International Conference on Mobile Computing and Networking (MobiCom 2017)

**Advisor Board Member**, Talk a Bit – Student Organized Tech Conference, 5<sup>th</sup> Edition (2017)

2016 Conference Chair, Talk a Bit – Student Organized Tech Conference, 4<sup>th</sup> Edition (2016)

Web Communication Co-chair, 2016 IEEE 19<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITSC 2016)

# VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

- 2017 **Student Volunteer (Media Coverage)**, 18<sup>th</sup> EPIA Conference on Artificial Intelligence (EPIA 2017)
  Porto, Portugal
- 2014 **Student Volunteer**, Inter-University Programming Marathon (MIUP 2014) Porto, Portugal

**Student Volunteer**, INForum - Symposion on Informatics (INForum 2014) Porto, Portugal

# Affiliations

- 2017– Institute for Systems and Technologies of Information, Control and Communication (INSTICC)
- 2013–2018 Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) as part of the University of Porto Student Branch (IEEE UP SB)

# AWARDS & HONORS

#### International

2017 **427<sup>th</sup>** (of 3350), IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 11.0, *ieee.org/xtreme* 

Online – Porto, Portugal

847<sup>th</sup> (of 2815), Google Hash Code 2017, hashcode.withgoogle.com

Online - Porto, Portugal

- 2015 **189<sup>th</sup>** (of 2477), IEEEXtreme 24h Programming Competition 9.0, *ieee.org/xtreme*Online Porto, Portugal
- 2014 **Honorable Mention**, IEEEmadC Mobile Application Development Contest, *ieeemadc.org*Online – Porto, Portugal

João Pedro Dias · Curriculum Vitæ · May, 2019

126<sup>th</sup> (of 2570), IEEEXtreme – 24h Programming Competition 7.0, ieee.org/xtreme
 Online – Porto, Portugal
 2<sup>nd</sup> Place, European BEST Engineering Competition, ebec.best.eu.org
 Warsaw, Poland

# Domestic

2018	6 <sup>th</sup> (of 31 Participants), CIBER PERSEU 2018 Portguese Army Exercise – Capture
	The Flag component by diateam, exercito.pt
	Portuguese Military Academy, Lisbon, Portugal
2011	1 <sup>st</sup> Place, PmatE Mat12 – Mathematics Competition, pmate.ua.pt University of Aveiro, Portugal
2009	<b>2<sup>nd</sup> Place</b> , PmatE Fis12 – Physics Competition, <i>pmate.ua.pt</i> University of Aveiro, Portugal

# ADDITIONAL TRAINING

2018	1 <sup>st</sup> UPTEC School on the Future of Computing, UPTEC – Science and Technology Park of University of Porto
2017	eq:cyberTalk: Security - Business Enablement, Multicert - Electronic Certification Services, S.A.
	$\label{eq:project_monogeneous} Project\ Management, \ \text{ERASMUS+ Mobility for teaching at Faculty of Engineering}, \\ \text{University of Porto}$
2016	$AWS\ Technical\ Essentials\ Online,\ Amazon\ Web\ Services-Training\ and\ Certification$
2015	Practical Workshop in Agile Project Management, Strongstep - Innovation in Software Quality
	$CERN\ Spring\ Campus,$ CERN - European Organization for Nuclear Research
2014	M101JS: MongoDB for Node.js Developers, MongoDB University (Online)

# **OPEN-SOURCE SOFTWARE**

I work on several open-source projects, all of which are available through my Github profile github.com/jpdias

2016	Botnet-Lab – github.com/jpdias/botnet-lab An IRC based tool for testing the capabilities of a botnet written in Python 2.7.
2016	Portfolio-Photo – github.com/jpdias/portfolio-photo An YAML and Jekyll (Ruby) dynamically generated photography portfolio using the Flickr API.

João Pedro Dias · Curriculum Vitæ · May, 2019

# 2014 Turing Machine – jpdias.me/TuringMachine/

A web-based Turing Machine with a pre-defined language, compiler and execution capabilites.

# PRO-BONO AND OTHER ACTIVITIES

#### ACADEMIC

2013–2015 **Executive Committee Member (Secretary)**, IEEE University of Porto Student Branch

Organization of several technical workshops and other events including *IEEE Day*, *IEEEXtreme* and *IEEEmadC*.

#### Humanitarian

2013–2015 Founder Member, Luz da Vida Youth Group

Organization of activities on behalf of the village community.

# Hobbies

2016–2017 **Football Player**, Grupo Desportivo e Recreativo de Travanca F.A.D.A. Amateur League, Amarante, Porto, Portugal

2008- Amateur Photographer - Wildlife, Landscapes and Travel

- Finalist at the Norte Multimédia Contest Photography Category, promoted by the Norte Portugal Regional Coordination and Development Commission (CCDR-N), 2018
- Finalist at the PORTUGAL NUM ISQUEIRO BIC® Contest, promoted by the I Love My BIC initiative by BIC Portugal, 2018
- $\it Exposition$  at Movimento d'Artes, promoted by the Cooperativa Cultural Vinha das Artes, 2010

### **LANGUAGES**

Portuguese Native

English B Level (Self-Evaluation)